Hi everyone, welcome. Today we're going
to be covering RCTs and large experiments
in big data settings.
This lecture has two goals. First, I want
to reinforce the poor logic and
randomized control trials.
Randomization is still the cleanest way
that we have to answer causal questions.
In my view, and I'll say this explicitly,
RCTs remain the gold
standard for research.
And they're feasible
and well implemented.
Second, I want to show you that logic
attracts the realities of big data.
Doing things like logging pipelines,
massive sample sizes.
Interference, multiple testing.
And the fact that statistical
significance becomes cheap
when your end is really huge.
So the theme of today is not to
experiment solve everything,
it's that experiments change the problem.
They eliminate some threats to inference
and introduce others.
So experiments are powerful because they
help answer causal questions and
observational data are ambiguous.
With observational data, you're always
asking whether the treatment and the
control group's different in ways you
didn't observe or couldn't measure.
Randomization solves that
on average by construction.
The big data changes the
scale and the failure modes.
Let me walk through the
four listed on this table.
So first, massive sample sizes.
Right here, this is a tiny
effect become detectable.
So you can get p-values near zero for
effects that have no
practical importance whatsoever.
So second, with logging pipelines,
outcomes often come from logging
pipelines, not from
carefully designed instruments.
So that introduces missingness,
measurement and silent breakage.
Third, inference for big social systems
often involves
interference and spillovers.
So users talk to each other, content
diffuses, networks overlap.
Several fails more often than we'd like.
And fourth, large scale experimentation
increases the risk of multiple testing
and adaptive hypotheses.
So we're running many variants, outcomes
and subgroups until something works.
So the headline here is simple.
Experiments don't magically save you.
They change the problems you have.
So this slide is doing
important conceptual work.
An experiment is not just random
assignment, it's a workflow.
So here's the things you have to do.
You have to define
your unit randomization.
You have to assign the treatment and
store that assignment.
You have to collect
outcomes often via logs.
You have to validate your measurement.
You have to analyze under
a pre-specified estimate.
And you have to
document the entire process.
In big data settings, failures rarely
happen at the randomization step.
They happen when assignments are
overwritten, when logs
change and when joins are wrong,
or when analysts don't agree on what the
outcome actually is.
So I want you to think of experiment as
an end-to-end data pipeline
with a causal interpretation.
Now is a single design choice.
So now let's talk about
the unit of randomization.
In big data experiments, common units
include users or
accounts, sessions, content items,
geographic clusters like zip codes or
counties, and institutions like
classrooms, schools, workplaces.
Your choice here matters a lot.
If you randomize the user level, you
usually get high power, but you may get
interference if users interact.
If you randomize the geographic or
cluster level, you reduce inference,
but you also reduce your effective sample
size and increase your variance.
I've seen experiments fail simply because
the unit of randomization didn't match
when the treatment actually operated.
For example, a treatment that affects a
shared feed but is
randomized at the user level
can produce misleading estimates because
users are exposed to
each other's treatment.
So the guiding principle is randomized at
the level where the
treatment actually operates.
So this slide is a
clarification more than anything else.
A-B tests all randomized control trials
in a pretty common
industry and in academic research.
They are the same ingredients, so we will
random assignment to A versus B,
outcomes measured through
instrumentation, and analysis focused on
average treatment effects.
What often gets lost in practice is the
question, "What is the estimate?"
So when people say A-B test, they often
mean we tried two versions
and looked at what happened.
When a researcher says RCT, they mean we
defined a causal question,
randomized unis, and estimated
a well-defined causal quantity.
So this slide is saying these are the
same thing in principle,
but only if you're clear
about what effect you're estimating.
So that's the best concepts coming in.
So what is an estimate?
An estimate is the precise causal
quantity you're trying to estimate.
It's not the method, it's not the
statistic, it's the target
causal effect defining words.
So a good estimate answers questions like
effect of what, on
whom, compared to what,
and over what time horizon.
So as a simple example, the average
effect of being assigned
to a new homepage layout
compared to the old one on user
click-through rates
over the next seven days.
So that sentence defines an estimate.
If you can state the estimate clearly in
words, you don't yet know what your
experiment is estimating.
So let's talk now about effective
assignment or ITT intention to trade.
ITT stands for attention to treat.
This is the effect of being assigned to a
treatment regardless of
whether the unit actually
complied, engaged, or used it.
So what's that in plain English?
Compared to everyone who was assigned A
with everyone who was
assigned B, no matter what
they actually did.
So why does ITT matter?
It preserves randomization, it answers
what happens if we roll
this out, and it's almost
always unbiased under
proper randomization.
So the A-B test example, you assign 50%
of users to a new
recommendation algorithm.
Some users ignore
recommendations entirely.
ITT still compares all assigned users,
not just those who clicked.
So this is the default and safest
estimate in big data experiments.
So then we have effect among those who
engaged, or TOT or LAT.
This is also what people want, but it's
much trickier to get.
So depending on context, this is called
TOT or treatment on
the treated or late local
average treatment effect.
So what are these in plain English?
The effect of the treatment among units
that actually received or used it.
So this is much harder to get.
It's because
engagement is not randomization.
People who engaged are usually different.
They're more motivated, they're more
active, they're more interested, and
they're systematically
different in unobserved ways.
So simply comparing engagers to
non-regained engagers
breaks randomization.
It's possible you can sometimes estimate
this using assignment
as an instrument, so this
is using like an instrumental variable
object, or strong
assumptions about compliance.
But this is no longer free causality.
You must justify your assumptions.
So many product teams report
impact among those who clicked.
The numbers often bias upward because
users are not randomized.
Then we have short and long-term effects.
This is about time horizons, which is
part of the estimate.
So for short-run effects, effects
measured immediately or
shortly after assignment.
Examples of them include same session,
same day, same week.
Exhaust and capture novelty effects,
curiosity, and initial attention.
But then we also have long-run effects.
So these effects are
measured with users' adapt.
So they're 30 days or later after
repeated exposure and
after learning your fatigue.
Long-run effects are often smaller,
different in size, and
they're more policy relevant.
So why does all this matter in A-B tests?
In big data, short-run
effects are easy to detect.
Long-run effects are harder
but often more meaningful.
If you don't specify the time horizon,
you don't know what
effect you're estimating.
So outcomes measured through
instrumentation, this is
how we can just think of it.
In a big data experiment, outcomes are
usually clicks, views,
events, logs, counters.
They're not natural variables.
They're constructed.
And this matters because we're logging
our definitions that can change.
Missing events look
like behavior changes.
And then we have things like boss or
automation that can skew our results.
So this slide is non-negotiable.
Assignment must be stored.
If you cannot reproduce assignment, you
cannot reproduce the experiment.
So if you can't reproduce your
assignment, what does that mean?
Your best practices are to do things like
log the assignment at the
moment of randomization,
use a stable unit ID, and prevent
re-randomization
through sticky assignment.
So here's a real failure
mode that might happen.
We have an assignment that was generated
dynamically based on a hash,
but the hashing logic
changes after deployment.
So the same user appeared in the
treatment and the
control at different times.
So nothing crashed here.
The experiment ran, but the causal
interpretation was gone.
So assignment is data.
Treat is durable, immutable, and audible.
So what is blocking stratification?
Blocking your stratification is a design
choice to improve precision.
You block on variables that are strongly
related to the outcome,
things like baseline activity, geography,
signup cohort, device
type, and platform type.
When you randomize within blocks, so that
means that each of these
blocks have an equal number of
control or treatment if we're doing a
completely randomized design.
So this kind of process doesn't bias your
experiment, it just reduces variance.
In big data settings, block is especially
valuable because
outcomes are often noisy.
Block unless you compare like with like
without increasing sample size.
So the key point is that blocking is a
design decision, not something you'd fix
later in your analysis.
So cluster randomization is common when
inference is likely,
when implementation
happens at a group level,
or when the treatment operates
through a shared environment.
So examples of these might include things
like a school, neighborhoods, workplaces,
network clusters, or communities.
The inference point here is crucial.
If you randomize at the cluster level,
you just analyze at the cluster level.
So this means that cluster robust
standard errors, randomization,
inference, and aggregation
to the unit of assignment.
So I've seen otherwise clean experiments
get invalidated because
analysts forgot this step
and treated individual observations as
independent when they weren't.
This slide is about the assumption that
underlies most causal inference methods,
including randomization experiments.
That assumption is called SEPFA, which
stands for the stable unit
treatment value assumption.
So SEPFA has two parts, but the one that
we care about here is first.
So each unit's outcome depends only on
its own treatment assignment, not on the
treatment assignment of other units.
So in plain English, SEPFA assumes no
inference between units.
If SEPFA holds them when I compare
treated and control units,
I'm isolating the causal
effect of the treatment itself.
So randomization is the rest.
The problem is that in big social
systems, SEPFA often fails.
So let me start with a case where SEPFA
would be reasonable for this.
Imagine a medical trial where patients
are randomly assigned to
receive a drug or a placebo,
and patients are
isolated from one another.
One person taking the drug does not
affect whether another
person's symptoms improve.
And that setting is reasonable to assume
that each patient's outcome depends only
on whether they receive the drug.
There's no meaningful
interaction between units.
So that's the world that SEPFA describes
and is the world that many
causal methods are designed for.
So when was SEPFA failed?
Let's change this to a social setting.
So in social systems, people interact,
they talk, they share resources, they
observe each other's behavior.
Information diffuses, congestion happens.
Because of that, one unit's treatment can
affect another unit's outcome.
So this is what we call
interference or spillovers.
So here's like a concrete
example to help motivate this.
Suppose a political campaign randomly
assigns households to receive campaign
mail encouraging turnout,
but the experiment is analyzed at the
individual voter level.
So one voter in a
household is officially treated.
The other voter in the same household is
unofficially at control.
So SEPFA wouldn't hold here because the
mail arrives at the household.
So people might talk about it, one person
might read it out loud, another person
might see it on the kitchen tabletop.
So this message can influence everyone in
the household, not just the individual
whose name was on the envelope.
So the untreated individual's outcome,
whether they turn out, now it depends on
someone else's treatment assignment.
So this would be a
direct violation of SEPFA.
And importantly,
randomization did not fail.
The experiment was randomized correctly.
The problem is that the unit of
randomization did not
match the unit of exposure.
So there's other common
examples of this in big data.
You can see this
everywhere in big data settings.
So on social media platforms, one user
seeing a new feature can affect what
content other friends see.
In recommendation systems, changing the
ranking for some users affects congestion
and availability for others.
In classrooms or workplaces, treating
some people changes the shared
environment for everyone.
In networks, information diffusion means
that exposure is really isolated.
So these are not edge
cases, they're the norm.
So when would a
randomization not protect you?
This is the key line on the slide and
it's worth repeating.
Randomization does not
protect you from interference.
Randomization guarantees balance and
expectation, but it does not guarantee
that units are causally isolated.
So if inference is present and you ignore
it, your estimate can be biased even if
perfect randomization in the experiment.
So the bias can be in either direction,
effects can be inflated, diluted, or even
flipped and signed
depending on how spillovers operate.
So what do we do when
we suspect interference?
There are several design strategies.
One is cluster randomization.
So instead of randomizing individuals,
you randomize groups, households,
classrooms,
neighborhoods, or network clusters.
So that inference happens within clusters
rather than across treatment and control.
Another approach is saturation designs
where you vary the proportion of treated
units within a cluster and
explicitly study spillovers.
You can also use buffer zones, so
excluding units where treatment
boundaries form analyses.
And then in some settings, you can
explicitly measure exposure such as the
number of treated neighbors or treated
friends and the outcome as a function of
exposure rather than assignment.
But the key idea is that when
interference is plausible, it has to be
designed for not ignored.
So with used sample size, tiny effects
can become statistically significant.
This is where many big data experiments
go wrong conceptually.
You should always report effect sizes in
meaningful units, uncertainty intervals,
minimal detectable effects, and where
appropriate cost-benefit
or welfare interpretation.
But also this is pretty bluntly.
A p-value is not a research contribution.
If an effect is statistically safe again
but practically meaningless, the right
conclusion is often this doesn't matter.
Big data forces you to care about
magnitude, not just detectability.
So big experiments naturally generate
many outcomes, variants, and subgroups.
That creates a series
multiple hypothesis testing problem.
Controls include pre-registration or
analysis plans, false discovery
readjustments, holdout outcomes, holdout
time windows, and hierarchical models.
The deeper point is about governance.
Big experiments create the temptation and
the ability to keep
looking until something works.
So without discipline, you will almost
certainly find something that looks
exciting but isn't real.
So before interpreting
results, you should run checks.
Balanced checks on
pretreatment covariates.
You should do AA tests
where nothing should differ.
placebo outcomes that should not move.
Incrementation checks to
ensure logs are stable.
These checks are not
about proving causality.
They're about catching
implementation failures early.
So in big systems,
many errors are silent.
Checks are how you surface them.
So now we can talk about known compliance
and missing outcomes.
This is where estimates really matter.
So the ITT effect is the effect of the
assignment is almost
always the safest quantity.
Estimating facts among the compilers can
be useful, but it requires additional
assumptions and careful interpretation.
The discipline here is simple.
Define your estimate first and then let
your analysis fall from that.
So how can we make experiments often
measured through logs?
This introduces specific risks.
If logging definitions change, you can
get artificial treatment effects.
If events drop, they can
look like behavior changed.
Bots, fraud, or automated activity can
contaminate your outcomes.
So the key principle here is the
assignment pipeline is
part of the experiment design.
Randomization doesn't
fix bad measurement.
So larger experiments typically store
data in logs, data
lakes, or feature stores.
So a common workflow
is you have a raw event.
Here you have clean data as a clean table
on it, and then you have
analysis for data sets for it.
So this is where your data scales matter.
If joins are wrong, time stamps are
misaligned, or IDs don't match, your
estimate is no longer
what you think it is.
Experiments and databases are inseparable
in big data settings.
So this slide introduces the
simplest estimator.
It's the difference in means.
The difference in means is unbiased for
the ITTF factor under randomization.
Regression adjustments can improve
precision if you include strong
predictors of the outcome.
But the key point is interpretive.
Randomization does the causal work.
Regression is there for
efficiency, non-identification.
So this slide shows a
conceptual assignment.
The point is not to memorize the code. It's to understand
the logic.
We have blocking here,
randomization, and assignment storage.
So in production, the hard part is not
generating random numbers.
It's ensuring assignment is sticky,
logged, and consistent over time.
This is an example of the same thing in
R, where we have our
synthetic data frame created here,
where there's blocking
and baseline activity.
We're grouping by D, which is in this
case the gene notation for treatment.
And we're looking at just the difference
in means between the trait
and the control group here.
And then we can fit it with robust
standard errors using this function here.
All right, this would just be how we set
up synthetic data in R.
And then again, I kind of
passed over quite quickly.
But if we use the estimator package in R
or something comparable in Python,
we can use our clusters here for robust
linear model entries.
So big data invites subgroup analyses,
but this can be quite risky.
For it, subgroups are often numerous.
Estimates are noisy and
false discoveries are common.
So safer approaches include things like
pre-specified subgroups, partial pooling,
and just honest estimation.
The discipline is to treat heterogeneity
as a model outcome, not
as a fishing expedition.
And one way to get around this is
pre-registering your
analytic approach for it.
So for example, whenever I read work that
says, okay, the treatment effect for
group A differs in direction,
or let's say, magnitude in group B.
That to me strikes me as a very common
way that someone's on
a fishing expedition.
So then I go back and I look for
pre-registration of hypotheses on it.
Another thing, and again, we emphasize
this throughout the class,
is reproducibility for large experiments.
So we want minimal reproducible
artifacts, things like
assignment table, raw data snapshots.
We want to look at our scripts that we
built, and then environment locks and
version parameters for it.
So the same type of consistency
throughout the course.
We want that also in our experiments.
So on with a few discussion questions for
you to keep in mind.
So what is the unit of
randomization in your research?
When, where would inference occur for it?
Which outcomes are fragile
because of logging on it?
Logging as in not logging the outcome
variable, logging
your decision rules here.
How do you prevent
multiple testing disasters for it?
So adjusting for multiple
comparisons, for example.
And then what does it mean for an effect
to be real at scale?
So keep that in mind.
In big data settings, real is going to
usually mean robust to reasonable
measurement variation,
save up your time,
interpretable and meaningful units,
and not an average effect of
instrumentation or
searching for our data.
And that's it for today.